<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="undefined"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Macavity: the Mystery Cat</title>
				<author>T. S. Eliot</author>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<p>Old Possum's Book of Practical Cats unsure of edition or provenance</p>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<p>Page images made available without knowledge of copyright.</p>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>This encoded file was created by Diane Jakacki and made available for a Linked
					Editing Academic Framework (LEAF) / LEAF-Writer workshop. This file is not meant
					for use or publication outside of the workshop environment.</p>
			</projectDesc>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div>
				<pb n="32"
					facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/training/main/getting_started/exercises/macavity_image1.jpg"/>
				<head> MACAVITY: THE MYSTERY CAT </head>
				<byline>
					<docAuthor>T.S. Eliot</docAuthor>
				</byline>
				<lg>
					<l>Macavity's a Mystery Cat: he's called the Hidden Paw</l>
					<l>For he's the master criminal who can defy the Law.</l>
					<l>He's the bafflement of Scotland Yard, the Flying Squad's despair:</l>
					<l>For when they reach the scene of crime—Macavity's not there!</l>
				</lg>


				<lg>
					<l>Macavity, Macavity, there's no one like Macavity,</l>
					<l>He's broken every human law, he breaks the law of gravity.</l>
					<l>His powers of levitation would make a fakir stare, </l>
					<l>And when you reach the scene of crime—Macavity's not there! </l>
					<l>You may seek him in the basement, you may look up in the air— </l>
					<l>But I tell you once and once again, Macavity's not there! </l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>Macavity's a ginger cat, he's very tall and thin; </l>
					<l>You would know him if you saw him, for his eyes are sunken in. </l>
					<l>His brow is deeply lined with thought, his head is highly domed; </l>
					<l>His coat is dusty from neglect, his whiskers are uncombed. </l>
					<l>He sways his head from side to side, with movements like a snake; </l>
					<l>And when you think he's half asleep, he's always wide awake. </l>
				</lg>

				<pb n="33"
					facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/training/main/getting_started/exercises/macavity_image2.jpg"/>

				<lg>
					<l>Macavity, Macavity, there's no one like Macavity, </l>
					<l>For he's a fiend in feline shape, a monster of depravity. </l>
					<l>You may meet him in a by-street, you may see him in the square- </l>
					<l>But when a crime's discovered, then Macavity's not there! </l>
				</lg>

				<lg>
					<l>He's outwardly respectable. (They say he cheats at cards.) </l>
					<l>And his footprints are not found in any file of Scotland Yard's. </l>
					<l>And when the larder's looted, or the jewel-case is rifled, </l>
					<l>Or when the milk is missing, or another Peke’s been stifled,</l>
					<l>Or the greenhouse glass is broken, and the trellis past repair- </l>
					<l>Ay, there's the wonder of the thing! Macavity's not there! </l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>And when the Foreign Office find a Treaty's gone astray, </l>
					<l>Or the Admiralty lose some plans and drawings by the way, </l>
					<l>There may be a scrap of paper in the hall or on the stair- </l>
					<l>But it's useless to investigate—Macavity's not there! </l>
					<l>And when the loss has been disclosed, the Secret Service say: </l>
					<l>"It must have been Macavityl"—but he's a mile away. </l>
					<l>You'll be sure to find him resting, or a-licking of his thumbs, </l>
					<l>Or engaged in doing complicated long division sums. </l>
				</lg>
				<lg>
					<l>Macavity, Macavity, there's no one like Macavity,</l>
					<l>There never was a Cat of such deceitfulness and suavity. </l>
				</lg>


				<note>NOTE: the stanzas above are broken down into line line groups (`lg`) and
					individual lines (`l`). Change the tagging of the lines below to match that
					above </note>
				<pb n="34"
					facs="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/LEAF-VRE/training/main/getting_started/exercises/macavity_image3.jpg"/>

				<p>He always has an alibi, and one or two to spare: At whatever time the deed took
					place-MACAVITY WASN'T / THERE! And they say that all the Cats whose wicked deeds
					are widely known (I might mention Mungojerrie, I might mention Griddlebone) Are
					nothing more than agents for the Cat who all the time Just controls their
					operations: the Napoleon of Crimel </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
